Guide to the Anderson Family Papers, 1901-1933
Department of Special Collections
Anderson Family Papers,
1901-1933
Special Collections M0171
Anderson family.
.5 linear ft (ca. 200 items).
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Robert Van Vleck Anderson, 1967.
Biographical Note
Family of Scottish-English origins which came to the United States in the middle of the nineteenth century. The family settled on the East Coast, later moving West; the Andersons contributed to society in the fields of theology, education and literature. Melville Best Anderson was an author, translator and teacher whose particular interest was the work of Dante. From 1891-1910, he taught in th English Department at Stanford University, serving as first chairman of the department.
Scope and Content
For information about this collection, refer also to the Anderson Family Papers, M51 and M111. This group of letters and assorted memorabilia dates from 1903 to 1933. Most of the correspondence is to or from Malcolm P. Anderson. There are many letters concerning Melville Anderson's translation of Dante.
Container List
- 1. 30 June 1901--Malcolm P. Anderson to Edward P. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. 5 June 1904--Robert V. V. Anderson to Melville B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 3. 28 May 1905--Ewald Flugel to Edward P. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 4. 29 Oct. 1905--Melville B. Anderson to his neice (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 5. 19 Aug. 1906--Robert Anderson to Melville Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 6. 14 Sept. 1906--Robert Anderson to Edward P. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 7. 18 Feb. 1907--Charlena VanVleck Anderson To Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 8. 6 May 1907--Malcolm P. Anderson to his aunt (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 9. 11 Jan. 1908--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 10. 5 May 1908--Robert Anderson to Frank (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 11. 17 July 1908--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 12. 11 Sept. 1908--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 13. 26 Oct. 1908--[Melville] B. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 14. 8 Nov. 1908--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 15. 22 Sept. 1909--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 16. 25 Dec. 1909--Robert Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 17. 25 May 1910--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 18. 17 Oct. 1911--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 19. 29 Nov. 1911--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 20. 29 April, 1912--Malcolm P. Anderson to Helen (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 21. 7 June, 1913--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 22. 22 Dec. 1914--Malcolm P. Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 23. Undated letter--Robert Anderson to Hattie B. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 24. Undated letter--Robert Anderson to Edward P. Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 25. 10 Dec. 1929--Edward Playfair Anderson to Malcolm B. Anderson. Favorable comments about translation of Dante. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 26. 6 Jan. 1930--Robert Anderson to Malcolm B. Anderson. Publication of Melville Anderson's translation of Dante by Oxford Press. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 27. 12 March 1930--Pagel Toynbee to M.B.A. -- The Publishing of M.B.A.'s translation of Dante in The World Classics Series by the Oxford Press. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 28. 1 July 1930--Pagel Toynbee to M.B.A.--M.B.A.'s agreement to publish his translation of Dante in the World Classics. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 29. 19 Nov. 1930--Edward P. Anderson to M.B.A.--tells of letter sent by M.B.A. to brother Edward which included letter from MBA's son (not in the collection). (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 30. 30 Nov. 1930--Edward P. Anderson to MBA-comments on approval by teachers at Columbia Univ. of MBA's work. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 31. 30 Dec. 1930--Pagell Toynbee--Publication of MBA's translation of Dante in the World Classics. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 32. 11 Jan 1931--Flowery praise for MBA's publication of the translation of Dante. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 33. 1 Feb. 1931--Robert Anderson to MBA--mention of a poem sent by Melville [perhaps copy of Divine Comedy]. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 34. 18 Feb. 1931--Robert Anderson to MBA--an unspecified sum of money sent along with this letter to help while rearranging his financial arrangements. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 35. 26 March 1931--Pagel Toynbee--concerning further information about MBA's translation of Dante in World Classics. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 36. 27 March 1931--Robert comments on poem Moon and Sequoia. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 37. 3 May 1931--Howard Judson Hall to MBA--comments on translation of Dante. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 38. 10 May 1931--Pagel Toynbee editing of translation of Dante to be published in The World Classics. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 39. 10 June 1931--Pagel Toynbee to MBA--editorial corrections of MBA's translation of Dante. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 40. 3 July 1931--Robert makes interesting observations on U. S. and French relations and comments on Presidents Hoover's policies. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 41. 7 July 1931--L. Ward Bannister--appreciation of Anderson's Dante by an Italian exile. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 42. 11 July 1931--Pagel Toynbee-further editorial correction of MBA's Dante. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 43. 17 July 1931--Pagel Toynbee-information about MBA's withdrawal of dedication of translation to Toynbee--also editorial changes (Box 1, Folder 5)
- [The following letters are to M. B. Anderson unless otherwise indicated.]
  - 44. 26 July 1931--Pagel Toynbee-World Classics. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 45. 1 Aug. '31--Robert Anderson (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 46. 16 Aug. 1931--Robert Anderson (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 47. 4 Sept 1931--Robert Anderson, on way to U.S.A. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 48. 12 Sept 1931--Robert Anderson in Washington D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 49. 19 Sept 1931--Robert Anderson at Stanford (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 50. 19 Sept 1931--[M.B. Anderson] to Mrs. Jordan on death of D.S. Jordan. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 51. 1 Oct 1931--Pagel Toynbee, N. Y. City. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 52. 7 Oct 1931--Robert Anderson at Stanford Univ. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 53. 15 Oct 1931--Robert Anderson at Los Angeles. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 54. 23 Oct 1931--Robt Anderson en rout through Kansas to East. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 55. 27 Oct 1931--Invitation from Geological Society of Washington, forwarded by Robt Anderson at Washington D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 56. 1 Nov 1931--Robt Anderson at Washington, D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 57. 12 Nov 1931--Howadji (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 58. 15 Nov 1931--Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 59. 17 Nov 1931--Arthur, cousin to MBA. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 60. 20 Nov 1931--Isabel, neice to MBA. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 61. 26 Nov 1931--train menu (Italian) with some handwritten lines on the back. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 62. 27 Nov 1931--Robt Anderson on board ship bet. New York and Europe. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 63. 30 Nov 1931--Robt Anderson on board ship bet. New York and Europe. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 64. 4 Dec 1931--Pagel Toynbee. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 65. 10 Dec 1931--Howadji at Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 66. 12 Dec 1931--Henry Deudon at Paris. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 67. 19 Dec 1931--Inez Gurnee at Appleton, Wis. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 68. 20 Dec 1931--Robert Anderson at El Biar, Algeria. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 69. 1 Jan 1932--Robt Anderson at El Biar, Algeria. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 70. 14 Jan 1932--Robt. Anderson at El Biar. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 71. 17 Jan 1932--Howadji at Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 72. 19 Jan 1932--Pagel Toynbee at N.Y. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 73. 19 Jan 1932--letter of recommendation from Geological Survey, Washington, to American Museum of Nat. History, N.Y., in praise of Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 74. 1 Feb, 1932, Jessie K. Jordan at Stanford; telegram on death of David S. Jordan. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 75. 3 Feb, 1932, Thomas MacBride, State Univ. of Iowa. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 76. 8 Feb, 1932, Howadji. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 77. 10 Feb, 1932, Robert Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 78. 12 Feb, 1932, Elizabeth Lossnig. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 79. 27 Feb, 1932, Robt Anderson at El Biar, Algeria. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 80. 5 March, 1932, Robt Anderson at El Biar, Algeria. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 81. 9 March, 1932, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 82. 28 March, 1932, Robt Anderson at Algeria. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 83. 8 April, 1932, Robt Anderson, in Spain. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 84. 26 April, 1932, Robt Anderson in Washington, D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 85. 29 April, 1932, T.H. MacBride at State Univ. of Iowa. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 86. 3 May, 1932, Robt Anderson, at Washington D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 87. 9 May, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 88. 12 May, 1932, Howadji, at Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 89. 12 May, 1932, Italian Ambassador to U.S. at Washington D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 90. 26 May, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 91. 3 June, 1932, Robt Anderson at Connecticut. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 92. 14 June, 1932, letter Oxford Univ. Press, England. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 93. 18 June, 1932, Robt Anderson on board ship bet. New York and Africa. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 94. 20 June, 1932, Howard J. Hall, Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 95. 27 June, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 96. 10 July, 1932, Howadji at Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 97. 21 July, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 98. 27 July, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 99. 8 Aug, 1932, Robt Anderson at Maine. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 100. 8 Aug, 1932, James Breasted to president of Rockefeller Foundation. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 111. 12 Aug, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 112. 20 Aug, 1932, Robt Anderson on board ship. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 113. 31 Aug, 1932, Howadji. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 114. 6 Sept, 1932, Robt Anderson on board ship off Newport, Rhode Island. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 115. 15 Sept, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 116. 29 Sept, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 117. 4 Oct, 1932, L.W. Bannister at Denver, Colo. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 118. 8 Oct, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 119. 25 Oct, 1932, Robt Anderson at Cambridge, Mass. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 120. 26 Oct, 1932, P.A. Martin at Stanford Univ. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 121. 29 Oct, 1932, Robt Anderson at Cambridge, Mass. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 122. 1 Nov, 1932, A.W. Smith at Ithaca, N.Y. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 123. 12 Nov, 1932, Robt Anderson at Cambridge, Mass. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 124. 26 Nov, 1932, L.W. Bannister at Denver, Colo. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 125. 29 Nov, 1932, Sec'ty of Interior at Washington, D.C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 126. 30 Nov, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 127. 18 Dec, 1932, Rachel, neice, at Brooklyn, N.Y. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 128. 19 Dec, 1932, Robt Anderson at New York. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 129. 19 Dec, 1932, E.O.J. at Mills College, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 130. 26 Dec, 1932, Howadji at Los Altos, Calif. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 131. 10 Jan, 1933, William Toynbee. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 132. 11 Jan, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 133. 13 Jan, 1933, Howard Judson Hall. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 134. 17 Jan, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 135. 20 Jan, 1933, Laura Huxtable Porter. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 136. 2 Feb, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 137. 16 Feb, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 138. 20 Feb, 1933, Howard Judson Hall. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 139. 12 March, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 140. 26 March, 1933, Howard Judson Hall. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 141. 28 March, 1933, telegram from Isabelle on Anderson's 82nd birthday. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 142. 9 April, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 143. 12 April, 1933, World Book Company Publishers. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 144. 18 April, 1933, Robert Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 145. 19 April, 1933, Limited editions Club, signed by George Macy. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 146. 24 April, 1933, World Book Company Publishers signed by Edward Bryant. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 147. 13 May, 1933, George L Hamilton. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 148. 20 May, 1933, Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 149. 28 May, 1933, George L. Hamilton. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Undated Letters
  - 150. Letter in child's hand to MBA on birthday, signed Patsy. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 151. Second letter from Patsy. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 152. letter in child's hand to Granther (presumably MBA) signed Bobby. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 153. letter from Barbara Aldeu to MBA. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 154. letter signed by Dorothea. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 155. letter signed by Dorothea. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 156. letter signed by Dorothea. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 157. Undated letter from Howard Judson Hall. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 158. From Edward, brother of Melville. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 159. From Robert Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 160. One page of letter from Robt Anderson. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- MISCELLANEOUS
  - 161. 23 March, 1933, Reminisciences of David Starr Jordan by MBA. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 162. Paget Toynbee: Some Personal Reminiscences, by Melville B. Anderson; reprint from the Romantic Review, Vol XXIII, No. 4. October--December, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 163. In Memoriam: Melville Best Anderson by J.L.G. reprint from the Romantic Review, Vol XXIV, No. 3. July--Sept, 1933. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 164. The Conservation of John Muir by Melville B. Anderson, reprint from the American [Museum] Journal, March, 1915. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 165. The Great Japanese Volcano Age by Robt Anderson, reprint from Popular Science Monthly July, 1907. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 166. Pleistocene Mazouna Stage in Western Algeria Containing Artifacts by Robt Anderson in bulletin of Geological Society of America, 1932. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 167. Typewritten copy of the Poem Symphony [by Melville B. Anderson?]. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 168. Copy of letter from Laura DeBosis, 26 April, 1931, to Mr. Bannister [L Ward Bannister, Counselor at Law, Denver, Colo] with comments on Anderson's Dante. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 169. One cartoon clipping from an unidentified newspaper. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 170. Entitled: les Cheveux Tombent et Les Illusions Demurent. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 171. Post card in French. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 172. One Page [#3 and 4] from On the Trail of Dante. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 173. One copy of La Cappuncina, an epistle to friends by Melville B. Anderson, 1912. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 174. Notes about David Starr Jordan by Melville B. Anderson (?) no date., 3 Pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 175. THE TWO NOBLE KINSMEN BY W.W. SKEAT, WITH M. B. ANDERSON'S COMMENTS ON FIRST PAGE (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 176. THE HAPPY TEACHER BY MELVILLE B. ANDERSON (Box 1, Folder 10)